[
  {
    "question": "From what Etruscan city did Lars Porsenna originate",
    "answer": "Clusium"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who saved Rome by his defense of the Pons Sublicius",
    "answer": "Horatius"
  },
  {
    "question": "Despite the legend of Horatius, historians believe Porsenna did capture Rome.  What tyrant of Cumae helped expel Lars Porsenna from Rome in 506 BC",
    "answer": "Aristodemus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What maiden swam the Tiber to escape Porsenna",
    "answer": "Cloelia*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who put his hand in a fire to convince Lars Porsenna of Roman resolve",
    "answer": "C. Mucius*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cognomen was given to C. Mucius after his demonstration to Lars Porsenna",
    "answer": "Scaevola*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does Scaevola mean",
    "answer": "lefty*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the son of Lars Porsenna",
    "answer": "Arruns"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where was Arruns finally defeated by Aristodemus of Cumae and the Latins in 506 BC",
    "answer": "Aricia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What son-in-law of T. Superbus gave him refuge after his expulsion and convinced the Latins to fight against Rome at Lake Regillus?",
    "answer": "Mamilius Octavius*"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what battle of 496 BC did Rome fight the Latin League",
    "answer": "Lake Regillus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What brothers came to Rome's aid during the Battle of Lake Regillus in 496 BC",
    "answer": "Castor and Pollux (Dioscuri)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What king of Cumae granted Tarquinius Superbus final refuge, where he died in 496 BC",
    "answer": "Aristodemus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What treaty of 493 BC was signed between Rome and the Latin League",
    "answer": "Foedus Cassianum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What plebeian leader negotiated the Foedus Cassianum",
    "answer": "Spurius Cassius"
  },
  {
    "question": "What Sabine chieftain was made a patrician of Rome in 504 BC",
    "answer": "Attus Claudius"
  },
  {
    "question": "What became the new name of Attus Claudius and his descendants",
    "answer": "Appius Claudius"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where was a Roman army trapped in 458 BC",
    "answer": "Mt. Algidus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was made dictator in 458 BC to rescue the army trapped at Mt. Algidus",
    "answer": "Cincinnatus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What tribe had trapped the Romans at Mt. Algidus",
    "answer": "Aequi"
  },
  {
    "question": "What general had been leading the troops trapped at Mt. Algidus",
    "answer": "Minucius*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What Roman led the Volsci against Rome in 491 BC",
    "answer": "Coriolanus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who persuaded Coriolanus to turn back his attack of Rome",
    "answer": "Veturia (mother) & Volumnia (wife)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What tribe did Coriolanus lead against Rome",
    "answer": "Volsci"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what battle of 479 BC was an army of the Fabii clan practically annihilated",
    "answer": "Cremera"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who led a Roman army to capture Fidenae, bridgehead to Veii, in 426 BC",
    "answer": "(C. Cornelius) Cossus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What special prize did Cossus win in 426 BC for killing his opposing general ",
    "answer": "spolia opima"
  },
  {
    "question": "What city did the Romans capture by tunnelling under the wall after a ten-year seige",
    "answer": "Veii"
  },
  {
    "question": "What general led the capture of Veii in 396 BC",
    "answer": "Camillus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was known as \"the second founder of Rome\"",
    "answer": "Camillus*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was meant by Cisalpine Gaul ",
    "answer": "area south of Alps (modern north Italy)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What small stream, 11 miles from Rome, was the site of a great battle on July 18, 390 BC",
    "answer": "Allia River"
  },
  {
    "question": "What name was given to July 18 on the Roman calendar, commemorating their defeat",
    "answer": "dies alliensis*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What creatures alarmed Romans of an attempt to capture the Capitol in 390 BC",
    "answer": "sacred Geese"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who heard the alarm of the sacred geese in 390 BC",
    "answer": "M. Manlius"
  },
  {
    "question": "What cognomen was given to M. Manlius after he saved the Capitol",
    "answer": "Capitolinus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What tribe captured Rome in 390 BC",
    "answer": "Senones"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the chief of the Senones who captured Rome",
    "answer": "Brennus*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What did Brennus say when the Romans complained of an unfair scale",
    "answer": "Vae victis (woe to the conquered)*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Though reportedly a project of Rome's 5th king, historians believe it probably wasn't begun until 378 BC.  What is it?",
    "answer": "Servian Wall"
  },
  {
    "question": "What enemy of Rome in the 4th and 3rd century BC occupied the south-central Apennines",
    "answer": "Samnites"
  },
  {
    "question": "What language did the Samnites speak",
    "answer": "Oscan*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What were the years of the First Samnite War",
    "answer": "343-341 BC"
  },
  {
    "question": "What town did the Samnite's attack and thus spark the First Samnite War",
    "answer": "Sidicini"
  },
  {
    "question": "What Campanian city's appeal brought Rome into the First Samnite War",
    "answer": "Capua"
  },
  {
    "question": "What war or revolt occurred from 340 to 338 BC",
    "answer": "Latin War/Revolt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where did Rome's decisive victory during the Latin Revolt occur",
    "answer": "Mt. Vesuvius*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who were the commanding generals over the Latins at Mt. Vesuvius",
    "answer": "Manlius Torquatus and Decius Mus*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was condemned to death by his father for disobedience though he killed his enemy",
    "answer": "Manlius Torquatus*"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year was the Latin League dissolved",
    "answer": "338 BC"
  },
  {
    "question": "What trophy was taken from the seaboard city of Antium during the Latin War",
    "answer": "prows of their ships became the rostra in forum*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where did the prows of the ships that formed the speaker's platform in Rome come from",
    "answer": "Antium*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the Samnite Wars was also called the Great Samnite War",
    "answer": "Second"
  },
  {
    "question": "What were the years of the Second Samnite War",
    "answer": "327-304/303 BC"
  },
  {
    "question": "What battle of 321 BC saw the Romans defeated by the Samnites",
    "answer": "Caudine Forks"
  },
  {
    "question": "What token of complete defeat and unconditional surrender was imposed on Rome in 321 BC",
    "answer": "forced to walk under the yoke"
  },
  {
    "question": "What general defeated the Romans at Caudine Forks",
    "answer": "Pontius*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where were the Romans disastrously defeated in 315 BC",
    "answer": "Lautulae"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the Roman general defeated at Lautulae",
    "answer": "Q. Fabius Rullianus*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What major ally of Rome changed sides during the 2nd Samnite War, but was retaken in 314",
    "answer": "Capua"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who devised the strategy that ultimately led to Roman victory in the 2nd Samnite War",
    "answer": "Appius Claudius Caecus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does Caecus mean",
    "answer": "the Blind"
  },
  {
    "question": "What two major building projects did Appius Claudius Caecus begin in 312 BC",
    "answer": "Aqua Appia and Via Appia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was Rome's first great aqueduct",
    "answer": "Aqua Appia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What road allowed Roman troops to move quickly to Capua in any weather",
    "answer": "Via Appia"
  },
  {
    "question": "What two cities the did the Via Appia originally connect",
    "answer": "Rome to Capua"
  },
  {
    "question": "What political office did Appius Claudius Caecus hold",
    "answer": "Censor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where did Fabius Rullianus defeat the Etruscan League in 310 BC",
    "answer": "Lake Vadimo"
  },
  {
    "question": "What were the years of the 3rd Samnite War",
    "answer": "298-290 BC"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what battle of 295 BC did the Romans defeat the Samnites",
    "answer": "Sentinum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What Roman general sacrificed himself to ensure Roman victory at Sentinum",
    "answer": "Decius Mus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was Decius Mus' act of self-sacrifice called",
    "answer": "devotio"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where in 283 BC were the Etruscan and Gallic allies of Samnium defeated",
    "answer": "Lake Vadimo"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who led the 283 BC defeat of Etruscans and Gauls at Lake Vadimo",
    "answer": "(P. Cornelius) Dolabella"
  },
  {
    "question": "What city hired Archidamas of Sparta, Alexander of Epirus, Cleonymus of Sparta, and Agathocles of Syracuse as mercenaries between 343 and 289 BC",
    "answer": "Tarentum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What city attacked and destroyed a Roman naval squadron in 282 BC",
    "answer": "Tarentum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was hired by Tarentum to fight Rome in 280 BC",
    "answer": "Pyrrhus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the kingdom of Pyrrhus, hired by Tarentum",
    "answer": "Epirus"
  },
  {
    "question": "From what land did Pyrrhus' 20 war elephants come",
    "answer": "India"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the first enemy to use elephants against Rome",
    "answer": "Pyrrhus of Epirus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term for a tactical victory which costs more than it gains",
    "answer": "Pyrrhic Victory"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what battle of 280 BC did Pyrrhus win a costly victory against Rome",
    "answer": "Heraclea"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who proclaimed, after fighting the Romans, \"with such an army I could conquer the world!\"",
    "answer": "Pyrrhus*"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what battle of 279 BC did Pyrrhus win another pyrrhic victory against Rome",
    "answer": "Asculum"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who declared in 279 BC \"another such victory and I am lost\".",
    "answer": "Pyrrhus"
  },
  {
    "question": "What Roman general refused to be bribed by Pyrrhus",
    "answer": "Fabricius*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What ambassador or Pyrrhus offered peace terms to the Senate which were refused",
    "answer": "Cineas*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was said to have conquered more nations with his tongue than Pyrrhus with his sword",
    "answer": "Cineas*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whose rousing speech led the Senate to refuse the peace terms offered by Cineas",
    "answer": "Appius Claudius Caecus*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who reported to Pyrrhus that the Roman senate was an \"assembly of kings\"",
    "answer": "Cineas*"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where did Pyrrhus take his army from 278 to 275 BC",
    "answer": "Sicily"
  },
  {
    "question": "What city requested Pyrrhus come to fight for them in 278 BC",
    "answer": "Syracuse"
  },
  {
    "question": "What empire did Pyrrhus fight against in Sicily from 278 to 275 BC",
    "answer": "Carthage"
  },
  {
    "question": "At what battle of 275 BC did Pyrrhus meet the Romans",
    "answer": "Maleventum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What became the new name of Maleventum after Pyrrhus was driven off there",
    "answer": "Beneventum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What Roman general won the battle of Beneventum",
    "answer": "Curius Dentatus*"
  },
  {
    "question": "What did the Romans use in response to Pyrrhus' elephants",
    "answer": "fiery spears*"
  },
  {
    "question": "How did Pyrrhus of Epirus ultimately die",
    "answer": "woman dropped pot on his head"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where did Pyrrhus of Epirus die",
    "answer": "Argos (in Greece, 272 BC)"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the modern name of Ariminum",
    "answer": "Rimini"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the modern name of Brundisium",
    "answer": "Brindisi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whose Italian campaign was a failure though he never lost a land battle",
    "answer": "Pyrrhus"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year did Tarentum finally surrender after the Pyrrhic War",
    "answer": "272 BC"
  },
  {
    "question": "What power controlled all of peninsular Italy by 264 BC, setting the stage for war with Carthage",
    "answer": "Rome"
  }
]